Preliminary Guide to the Faith Holsaert Papers, 1950-2011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Faith Holsaert papers 1950-2011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Holsaert, Faith.
Extent: 6525 items 10.2 linear feet
Civil Rights and LGBT community activist. Correspondence, newsletters, publications, and other materials relating to the activities of Faith Holsaert from the 1960s to the present. A large portion of the collection consists of correspondence and ephemera from her involvement in the Civil Rights movement, including SNCC, and the women's rights movement. Also includes materials from the writing and publishing of Hands on the Freedom Plow, some of which is restricted. The collection also has a large amount of personal memorabilia and materials relating to Holsaert's childhood and family. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
RL.00566
Language: Materials in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research, but has restrictions.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
Gift, 2008 (2008-0277), 7.5 lin. ft.
Gift, 2010 (2010-0220), 1.2 lin. ft.
Gift, 2011 (2011-0150), 1.5 lin. ft.
Biographical / Historical Note
Civil Rights and LGBT community activist.
Collection Overview
Correspondence, newsletters, publications, and other materials relating to the activities of Faith Holsaert from the 1960s to the present. A large portion of the collection consists of correspondence and ephemera from her involvement in the Civil Rights movement, including SNCC, and the women's rights movement. Also includes materials from the writing and publishing of Hands on the Freedom Plow, some of which is restricted. The collection also has a large amount of personal memorabilia and materials relating to Holsaert's childhood and family. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Subject Headings
Holsaert, Faith; Homosexuality; Civil rights movement -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Feminism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Voter registration -- Georgia; Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (U.S.); Pamphlets; VHS; CD-ROMs; Audiocassettes; Correspondence; Newsletters; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
Contents of Collection
- Faith Holsaert Papers, 1950-2011, 10 Boxes
  The collection has been reboxed, and minimal processing has been completed.
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Childhood: Faith and Shai/Deb, 1950s (Box 1)
    - Candy Keely/Carole Gordon/Amina (Box 1)
    - Letters from Writing Friends (Box 1)
    - To my mother (Box 1)
    - From James Holsaert (Box 1)
    - Jan Chapin, 1972-1982 (Box 1)
    - Crosing (Faith and Shai's godparents) (Box 1)
    - Hillel, Lickert, Celia (Box 1)
    - From Shai, 1978-1984 (Box 1)
    - Madre, 1960s (Box 1)
    - Eunice Holsaert, 1970s (Box 1)
    - Cora, Patricia, and Pauline Holsaert (Box 1)
    - Charity Bailey (Box 1)
    - Friends, etc., 1960s (Box 1)
    - Friends, 1970s, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Friends, 1980s (Box 1)
  - West Virginia
    - Appalachia (Box 1)
    - Recht Dee (Box 1)
    - Pauley case (Box 1)
    - Rainbow (WV and SREP) (Box 1)
    - Lesbian community newsletters (Box 1)
    - Women's Health Center, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
    - WV Rainbow Univ. Healthcare (Box 1)
  - Coal Employees project (Box 1)
  - Hamlet, NC (Box 1)
  - Gulf Coast Tenants (Box 1)
  - Guardian (Box 1)
  - Furniture Workers 282 (Box 1)
  - Political Prisoners (Box 2)
  - Pittston Company (Box 2)
  - Anti-KKK (Box 2)
  - Southern Org. Committee for Economics and Social Justice (Box 2)
  - Project South (Box 2)
  - Unfoldered miscellaneous materials (Box 2)
  - Sentimental (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Daddy/Betty/Shai (Box 2)
  - Cash Response (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Jan letters (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1988-1994, (8 folders) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 2001 (Box 2)
  - Cuban coins (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1994-1999, (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Bibliographic annotations, 1986, (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Book reviews, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Bibliographic annotations, 1982, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Summer work archive, 1983 (Box 3)
  - SNCC interview transcript (Box 3)
  - Chatfield book (Box 3)
  - Klekotka Master's Thesis (Box 3)
  - Interviews with Me Archive (Box 3)
  - Self (Box 3)
  - Madre (Box 3)
  - Daddy: appraisals (Box 3)
  - Daddy: legal and administrative II (Box 3)
  - Faith and Hillel (Box 3)
  - Family chronology, 1987 Dec. (Box 3)
  - Froggy album, 1990 Dec. (Box 3)
  - Shai (Box 3)
  - Carmela, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Dance (Box 3)
  - Conspiracy in Coal booklet (Box 4)
  - Brief of Contestants Urging the Vacating of Seats, U.S. House of Representatives (Box 4)
  - Brief submitted by the Miss. Freedom Democratic Party (Box 4)
  - South
    - SCEF Society (Box 4)
    - Asbestosis (Box 4)
    - Anne Braden (Box 4)
    - Rainbow SREP (Box 4)
    - Black elected officials (Box 4)
    - Center for Democratic Renewal (Box 4)
    - Christie Institution (Box 4)
    - Cold War (Box 4)
    - KKK (Box 4)
    - Lexington women's prison (Box 4)
    - Movement support network (Box 4)
    - NCARRV (Box 4)
    - Poultry workers (Box 4)
    - SOS Article (Box 4)
    - Robeson Co., N.C. (Box 4)
    - Up and Out of Poverty (Box 4)
    - SE Project (Box 4)
    - So Fight Back (Box 4)
    - SOC Environmental Justice (Box 4)
    - SOC (Box 4)
    - SOC Youth (Box 4)
    - SOC Labor (Box 4)
    - SOC, 1996 (Box 4)
    - SOC Newletter (Box 4)
    - SOC Board (Box 4)
    - Freedomways, 1964 (Box 4)
    - KKK: A History of Racism and Violence (Box 4)
    - Freedom is a Constant Struggle program (Box 4)
    - AmeriKKKa, 1995 (Box 4)
    - Frederick Douglass (Box 4)
    - Mississippi Eyewitness, 1964 (Box 4)
    - Life and Times of Frantz Fanon (Box 4)
    - Miss., Summer 1964 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous unfoldered materials (Box 4)
    - Miss. Baker Conference, 2000 (Box 4)
    - SNCC, 1988 (Box 4)
    - SNCC (Box 4)
    - Revolution in Mississippi (Box 4)
    - Mississippi: Subversion of the Right to Vote (Box 4)
    - Mississippi Summer Project (Box 4)
    - Cracking the Color Line (Box 4)
    - Racism (Box 4)
    - The Trial of Bobby Seale (Box 4)
    - On the Ideology of the Black Panther Party (Box 4)
    - A White American in an Unwhite World (Box 4)
    - The Angry Children of Malcolm X (Box 4)
    - Position Progress of Black America, 1967 (Box 4)
  - Southwest Georgia
    - From friends and family while Faith was in SWGA, 1962-1963 (Box 4)
    - SW Ga. letters (Box 4)
    - Christian family and others (Box 4)
    - Harrison thesis (Box 4)
    - CB King (Box 4)
    - Special Report: Albany, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook pages with newspaper clippings (Box 4)
    - Voter's Registration Drive, 1962-1963 (Box 4)
    - Albany, Ga., newsletter, 1962-1963 (Box 4)
    - Albany, Ga. (Box 4)
  - Women (Box 5)
    - Off Our Backs: A Women's News Journal, 1980 Nov. (Box 5)
    - Women: A Journal of Liberation, 1970 (Box 5)
    - The Feminist Art Journal, 1974-1975 (Box 5)
    - Aphra (vol. 5, no. 1), 1973-1974 (Box 5)
    - Quest: Feminist Quarterly, 1975 (Box 5)
    - Woman News, 1980 (Box 5)
    - Chrysalis: A Magazine of Women's Culture (No. 10) (Box 5)
    - Up from Under (vol. 1, no. 4) (Box 5)
    - Up from Under (vol. 1, no. 3), 1971 Jan., (2 copies) (Box 5)
    - Women's Health (Box 5)
    - Women W. Va. (Box 5)
    - Lesbian feminist (Box 5)
    - Socialist feminist (Box 5)
    - Women and labor (Box 5)
    - Second Wave (vol. 3, no. 1) (Box 5)
    - Yale Law Journal: Equal Rights Amendment, 1971 Apr. (Box 5)
    - Ramparts, 1974 Sept. (Box 5)
    - Our Bodies, Our Selves, 1971 (Box 5)
    - Women's Free Express, 1974 Mar.-Sept., (3 pamphlets) (Box 5)
    - Southern Voices (Box 5)
    - Motive: Lesbian/Feminist issue, 1972 (Box 5)
    - The Second Wave (vol. 2, no. 4) (Box 5)
    - Up from Under, 1971-1972 (Box 5)
    - Up from Under (vol. 1, no. 2) (Box 5)
    - Women/Coal (Box 5)
    - Women (Box 5)
    - Sterilization abuse (Box 5)
    - Homophobia (Box 5)
    - Lesbian battery (Box 5)
    - Feminist Revolution: Redstockings, 1975 (Box 5)
    - Socialist Feminism: A Strategy for the Women's Movement, 1972 (Box 5)
    - Heterosexuality (Box 5)
  - Radical/Left
    - Kathy Boudin, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Left/Marxist (Box 5)
    - On the Issues: The Progressive Women's Quarterly, 1995 (Box 5)
    - Two Interviews: Corky Gonzalez and ChaCha Jimenez, 1970 (Box 5)
    - The Guy Who Controls Your Future (Box 5)
    - The Communist Manifesto (Box 5)
    - Hard Times in Detroit, 1971 (Box 5)
    - GE: Profile of a Corporation, 1967 (Box 5)
    - Consumption: Domestic Imperialism (Box 5)
    - PLP: A Critique (Box 5)
    - Problems of U.S. Capitalism (Box 5)
    - They Say, All Women Must Be Commandos (Box 5)
    - Tierra-O-Muerte (Box 5)
    - Monthly Review: An Independent Socialist Magazine
      - 1978 July-Aug. (Box 5)
      - 1979 Mar. (Box 5)
      - 1979 Apr. (Box 5)
      - 1979 July-Aug. (Box 5)
      - 1979 Dec. (Box 5)
    - Race and Class (vol. 35, no. 2-3) (Box 5)
    - If an Agent Knocks: Federal Investigation and Your Rights (Box 5)
    - U.S. Capitalism in Crisis, 1978 (Box 5)
    - To Feel Within the Water (Box 5)
    - Repression and Resistance: An Information Manual (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 5)
  - Black Power: Music of a Revolution (CD-ROM) (Box 5)
  - Voices of Pacifica (VHS) (Box 5)
  - Untitled minidisk (Box 5)
  - Hands on the Freedom Plow materials
    - Editors' Correspondence, 2000-2007 (Box 6)
      RESTRICTED.
    - Correspondence, 1995-2002 (Box 6)
    - Book press, 2010 and undated (Box 6)
    - Book proof, 2010 (Box 6)
    - University of Illinois Press memorandums and book editors, 2005-2007 (Box 6)
    - University of Illinois Press marketing for book, 2010 (Box 6)
    - Drafts and revisions, 2009 and undated (Box 6)
    - Revisions for bridges, 2008 (Box 6)
    - First review and annotations, 2007-2008 (Box 6)
    - CDs of text (removed to Duke's electronic records server) (Box 6)
    - Book structure, 2000-2006 (Box 6)
    - Address list for manuscripts and edit team assignments, 1997-2006 (Box 6)
    - Contract/business, 2007 (Box 6)
    - Introductions and bridges for final introduction, 2005-2007 and undated (Box 6)
    - Background research articles, 1996-1997 and undated (Box 6)
    - Business and finances, 1997 (Box 6)
    - Meeting minutes and progress reports, 2006-2007 (Box 6)
    - Letters to contributors, 1996-2007 (Box 7)
    - Brown, Marie: Correspondence and comments, 1998-1999 (Box 7)
    - Baker, Ella: "The Black Woman in the Civil Rights Struggle: A Long View," 1969 (Box 7)
    - Sarah Lawrence Conference, 2002-2003 (Box 7)
    - Interviews and SGWA texts, 1962 and undated (Box 7)
    - Presses other than University of Illinois, 2000-2004 (Box 7)
    - Drafts, 2000, (3 folders) (Box 8)
    - Drafts and editorial notes, 2000 (Box 9)
    - Manuscript sections 1 and 2, 2002 July (Box 9)
    - Drafts and editing, 2002 July, (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - Drafts, 2003 Sept. (Box 9)
    - Binder/drafts, 2006, (folder 1 of 4) (Box 9)
    - Binder/drafts, 2006, (folders 2 to 4) (Box 10)
    - Publicity, (2 pamphlets) (Box 10)
  - Audiovisual materials
    - Interview of Faith Holsaert, 2006 April 4, (CD-ROM) (Box 10)
    - Joanne C.M., 1997 July 9, (2 Cassettes) (Box 10)
    - Jamie C.R., 1997 July 6, (Microcassette) (Box 10)
    - Ratha, 1997 July 7, (Cassette) (Box 10)
    - Carolyn D., undated, (Cassette) (Box 10)
    - McCree, 1997 July, (Cassette) (Box 10)
    - Unknown title, (Cassette) (Box 10)
  - Oversized Materials
    - Hands on the Freedom Plow poster (Opaperfolder 1)